The work of a transportation commissioner
إن عمل مفوّض النقل
isn't just about stop signs and traffic signals.
لا يقتصر فقط على اشارات "قف" واشارات السير
It involves the design of cities
بل يتضمن كذلك تصميم المدن
and the design of city streets.
وشوارع المدن
Streets are some of the most valuable resources
الشوارع هي من أهم العناصر
that a city has, and yet it's an asset
التي تمتلكها المدينة قيمة كبيرة
that's largely hidden in plain sight.
مخفية على مرأى من الجميع
And the lesson from New York
والدرس من مدينة نيويورك
over the past six years
على مدار ال 6 سنوات الماضية
is that you can update this asset.
هو أنكم قادرون على تطوير هذا الكنز
You can remake your streets quickly, inexpensively,
بإمكانكم اعادة تصميم شوارعكم بسرعة وبأقل تكلفة
it can provide immediate benefits,
وذلك قد يدّر فوائد مباشرة
and it can be quite popular.
بالإضافة الى الشهرة الواسعة
You just need to look at them a little differently.
يجب عليك فقط أن تنظر لها(الشوارع) بطريقة مختلفة قليلا
This is important because we live in an urban age.
هذا مهم جدا لاننا نعيش في عصر التحضّر
For the first time in history,
لأول مرّة في التاريخ
most people live in cities,
الناس يسكنون في المدن
and the U.N. estimates that over the next 40 years,
والامم المتحدة تقدّر أنه خلال ال 40 سنة المقبلة
the population is going to double on the planet.
سيتضاعف عدد السكان على هذا الكوكب
So the design of cities is a key issue for our future.
لذلك تصميم المدن هو مفتاح الحل في المستقبل
Mayor Bloomberg recognized this
عمدة مدينة"بلومبيرغ" أدرك ذلك
when he launched PlaNYC in 2007.
عندما أطلق مشروع PlaNYC عام 2007
The plan recognized that cities
أقرّت الخطة بأن المدن
are in a global marketplace,
هي جزء من السوق العالمية
and that if we're going to continue to grow and thrive
واذا كنّا نرغب بمتابعة النمو والازدهار
and to attract the million more people
ولجذب المليون شخص
that are expected to move here,
المتوقع انتقالهم الى هنا
we need to focus on the quality of life
علينا أن نركز على نوعية الحياة
and the efficiency of our infrastructure.
وفعالية بنيتنا التحتية
For many cities, our streets have been
بالنسبة لعدد من المدن , شوارعنا كانت
in a kind of suspended animation for generations.
أشبه برسوم متحركة تم وقفها لأجيال
This is a picture of Times Square in the '50s,
هنا صورة لساحة " تايمز سكوير" في الخمسينيات
and despite all of the technological innovation,
وبالرغم من كل التطور التكنولوجي
cultural changes, political changes,
والتغييرات الثقافية والتغيرات السياسية
this is Times Square in 2008.
هذه هي "تايمز سكوير" عام 2008
Not much has changed in those 50 years.
لم تتغير كثيرا خلال الخمسين عاما الماضيات
So we worked hard to refocus our agenda,
لذلك عملنا جاهدين لتركيز جدول أعمالنا
to maximize efficient mobility,
لرفع التنقل لأقصى فعالية ممكنة
providing more room for buses, more room for bikes,
وذلك بتوفير المزيد من المساحة للباصات والدراجات
more room for people to enjoy the city,
والمزيد من المساحة للناس كي يستمتعو بالمدينة
and to make our streets as safe as they can be
ولجعل شوارعنا آمنة قدر المستطاع
for everybody that uses them.
لكل من يستخدمها
We set out a clear action plan
لقد وضعنا خطة عمل واضحة
with goals and benchmarks.
مع الاهداف والمعايير
Having goals is important,
امتلاك الاهداف هو شيء مهم جدا
because if you want to change and steer the ship
فعندما ترييد تغيير ووجهة
of a big city in a new direction,
تطوّر المدينة في اتجاه جديد
you need to know where you're going and why.
يجب عليك أن تعرف على الاقل وجهتك ولماذا هذه الوجهة
The design of a street can tell you everything
تصميم شارع بامكانه اخبارك بكل شيء
about what's expected on it.
حول ما هو متوقع على ذلك
In this case, it's expected that you shelter in place.
في هذه الحالة بإمكانك أن تأوي في مكان ما.
The design of this street is really
تصميم الشارع هو فعلا
to maximize the movement of cars
لزيادة حركة السيارات للحد الاقصى
moving as quickly as possible
وبالسرعة القصوى
from point A to point B,
من النقطة "أ" الى النقطة "ب"
and it misses all the other ways
وهذا يفتقد كل الطرق الأخرى
that a street is used.
التي يتم استخدام الشارع بها
When we started out, we did some early surveys
قبيل البدأ قمنا ببعض الاحصاءات
about how our streets were used,
عن كيفية استخدام الطرق
and we found that New York City was largely
ووجدنا أن مدينة نيويورك كانت بشكل كبير
a city without seats.
مدينة بلا مقاعد
Pictures like this, people perched
صور كهذه , أناس جالسة
on a fire hydrant, not the mark of a world-class city.
على صنبور الاطفائية ,ليست علامة على مدينة من الطراز الأول
(Laughter)
(صوت ضحك)
It's not great for parents with kids.
هذا ليس جيّدا للعائلات
It's not great for seniors. It's not great for retailers.
ليس جيّدا للمسنين . ليس جيّدا لأصحاب المتاجر
It's probably not good for the fire hydrants.
على الاغلب ليس جيّدا لصنبور الاطفائية
Certainly not good for the police department.
وبشكل قاطع ليس جيدا لقسم الشرطة
So we worked hard to change that balance,
لذلك عملنا جاهدين لتغيير هذا التوازن
and probably the best example of our new approach
وربما أفضل مثال لنهجنا الجديد
is in Times Square.
في ساحة " تايمز سكوير"
Three hundred and fifty thousand people a day
50300 شخص يوميا
walk through Times Square,
يمرّون عبر "تايمز سكوير"
and people had tried for years to make changes.
وأناس حاولت لسنوات لعمل التغيير
They changed signals, they changed lanes,
لقد غيّرو الاشارات , غيّرو الممرات
everything they could do to make Times Square work better.
كل شيء لجعل "تايمز سكوير" يعمل بشكل أفضل
It was dangerous, hard to cross the street.
لكد كان خطرا وصعبا أن تحاول عبور الشارع
It was chaotic.
لقد كان كارثيا
And so, none of those approaches worked,
لذلك لا شيء من هذه المحاولات نجح فعلا
so we took a different approach, a bigger approach,
لذلك أخذنا نهجا جديدا , نهجا أضخم
looked at our street differently.
لقد نظرنا الى شوارعنا بطريقة مختلفة
And so we did a six-month pilot.
ولذلك قمنا بتجربة ل 6-أشهر
We closed Broadway from 42nd Street to 47th Street
قمنا بإغلاق "بروودواي" من شارع 42 الى 47
and created two and a half acres
وصنعنا 2.5 فدّان
of new pedestrian space.
من المساحة لممرات المشاة
And the temporary materials are an important part
وكذلك المواد المؤقتة هي جزء هام
of the program, because we were able to show
من هذا البرنامج حيث استطعنا عرض
how it worked.
كيفية عملها
And I work for a data-driven mayor, as you probably know.
وانا اعمل في بلدية تعتمد على البيانات كما تعلمون
So it was all about the data.
لذا فكل شيء يدور حول البيانات
So if it worked better for traffic, if it was better for mobility,
لذا لو نجحت في السير , والحركة
if it was safer, better for business, we would keep it,
واذا كانت أؤمن وافضل من اجل الاعمال فسوف نحافظ عليها
and if it didn't work, no harm, no foul,
اما ان لم تنجح الفكرة , فلا أذى ولا ضرر
we could put it back the way that it was,
ونحن قادرون على اعادة الامور الى ما كانت عليه في السابق
because these were temporary materials.
لأن هذه المواد كانت مؤقتة
And that was a very big part of the buy-in,
وقد كان ذلك جزءا كبيرا في عمليت الشراء
much less anxiety when you think that something
يسبب أقل قلق عندما تعلم مسبقا
can be put back.
انه يمكنك إرجاع كل شيء كما كان سابقا
But the results were overwhelming.
ولكن النتائج كانت ساحقة
Traffic moved better. It was much safer.
تحرك السير بشكل أفضل وأصبح أكثر أمنا
Five new flagship stores opened.
خمسة متاجر رائدة جديدة افتتحت
It's been a total home run.
لقد كانت عودة للوطن من جديد
Times Square is now one of the top 10
والان "تايمز سكوير" هو واحد من أفضل عشرة
retail locations on the planet.
مواقع لبيع التجزئة على هذا الكوكب
And this is an important lesson,
وهذا درس مهم لللغاية
because it doesn't need to be a zero-sum game
لأنها لا يتوجّب عليها أن تكون لعبة بدون اي فائدة
between moving traffic and creating public space.
بين تحريك السير وانشاء المساحات للعامة
Every project has its surprises,
لكل مشروع مفاجآته الخاصة به
and one of the big surprises with Times Square
وواحدة من أكبر المفاجآت في "تايمز سكوير"
was how quickly people flocked to the space.
هو سرعة توافد الناس الى هذه المساحات
We put out the orange barrels,
لقد وضعنا البراميل برتقالية اللون
and people just materialized immediately into the street.
ثم توافد الناس الى الشارع على الفور
It was like a Star Trek episode, you know?
لقد كان أشبه بحلقة"ستار تريك" أليس كذلك ؟
They weren't there before, and then zzzzzt!
لا أحد هناك ثمّ فجأة ! "زززز"
All the people arrived.
امتلىء المكان بالناس
Where they'd been, I don't know, but they were there.
أين كانو؟ لا أعلم ولكنهم أصبحو هنا
And this actually posed an immediate challenge for us,
حقيقة , لقد طرح هذا تحد فوري لنا
because the street furniture had not yet arrived.
لأن مزيّنات الشوارع لم يصل بعد
So we went to a hardware store
لذا ذهبنا الى متجر للمعدّات
and bought hundreds of lawn chairs,
واشترينا المئات من كراسي الحدائق
and we put those lawn chairs out on the street.
ووضعنا هذه الكراسي على الشوارع
And the lawn chairs became the talk of the town.
واصبحت حديث البلدة
It wasn't about that we'd closed Broadway to cars.
لم يكن الحديث عن اغلاق شارع "برود وي" امام السيارات
It was about those lawn chairs.
بل كان الحديث عن هذه الكراسي
"What did you think about the lawn chairs?"
"ما رأيك بهذه الكراسي؟"
"Do you like the color of the lawn chairs?"
"هل يعجبك لونها ؟ "
So if you've got a big, controversial project,
لذا ان امتلكت مشروع كبير مثير للجدل
think about lawn chairs.
فكّر بمقاعد الحدائق
(Laughter)
"ضحك"
This is the final design for Times Square,
هذا هو التصميم النهائي ل "تايمز سكوير"
and it will create a level surface,
ذلك سينشىء سطح مستو
sidewalk to sidewalk,
من الرصيف للرصيف
beautiful pavers that have studs in them
ارصفة جميلة مرصّعة
to reflect the light from the billboards,
لتعكس الضوء من اللوحات
creating a great new energy on the street,
تنشىء طاقة جديدة في الشارع
and we think it's going to really create
ونحن نعتقد أنه سيؤسس
a great place, a new crossroads of the world
لمكان رائع , مفترق طرقات العالم الجديدة
that is worthy of its name.
تستحق اسمها
And we will be cutting the ribbon on this,
وسنقوم بقص الشريط في هذا المشروع
the first phase, this December.
لبداية المرحلة الاولى في ديسيمبر
With all of our projects, our public space projects,
بجميع مشاريعنا , ومشاريع المساحات العامة
we work closely with local businesses
نحن نعمل بالتعاون مع الشركات المحلية
and local merchant groups
والمجموعات التجارية المحلية
who maintain the spaces, move the furniture,
التي تحافظ على المساحة وتحرّك الاثاث الى الشارع
take care of the plants.
وتهتم للنباتات
This is in front of Macy's, and they were
هذا من أمام "ماسيز" لقد
a big supporter of this new approach,
كانو داعم حقيقي لنا في هذا المشروع الجديد
because they understood that more people on foot
لأنهم أيقنو ان المزيد من الناس الين يمشون على اقدامهم
is better for business.
سيكون أفضل للتجارة
And we've done these projects all across the city
ولقد قمنا بهذه المشاريع في جميع انحاء المدينة
in all kinds of neighborhoods.
وفي جميع الاحياء
This is in Bed-Stuy, Brooklyn,
هذه هي "بيد-ستاي" , "بروكلين" (أحياء في مدينة نيويورك -المترجم)
and you can see the short leg that was there,
حيث تستطيع ان تشاهد النقص هنا
used for cars, that's not really needed.
حيث يتم استخدام سيارات لا حاجة لها
So what we did is we painted over the street,
لذا ما قمنا به هو رسم على الشارع
put down epoxy gravel, and connected the triangle
لقد وضعنا الايبوكسي لربط الحصى وربطنا المثلث
to the storefronts on Grand Avenue,
الى الواجهة الامامية لمتجر " غراند أفينو"
created a great new public space,
منشئين بذلك مساحة عامّة كبيرة
and it's been great for businesses
وهذا شيء عظيم لتجارة
along Grand Avenue.
"غراند أفينو"
We did the same thing in DUMBO, in Brooklyn,
لقد فعلنا الشيء نفسه في " دامبو" في "بروكلين"
and this is one of our first projects that we did,
وكان هذا من اوائل مشروعاتنا التي نفذّت
and we took an underutilized,
لقد اخذنا
pretty dingy-looking parking lot
مصفّ مهمل وغير مستغل
and used some paint and planters
واستخدمنا الدهان والنباتات
to transform it over a weekend.
لتحويل هذا المكان الى عطلة نهاية الاسبوع
And in the three years since we've implemented the project,
ومنذ ثلاث سنوات مذ قمنا بتجهيز المشروع
retail sales have increased 172 percent.
لقد زادت التجارة بنسبة 172%
And that's twice that of adjacent areas in the same neighborhood.
وهذا ضعف ما هو موجود في اماكن قريبة في الحي
We've moved very, very quickly
لقد تقدمنا بسرعة كبيرة جدا
with paint and temporary materials.
مستخدمين الدهان والمواد البدائية
Instead of waiting
بدل من الانتظار
through years of planning studies
لسنوات من دراسات التخطيط
and computer models to get something done,
ونماذج محوسبة حتى نقوم بشيء ما
we've done it with paint and temporary materials.
لقد قمنا بذلك بالدهانات وببعض المواد البدائية
And the proof is not in a computer model.
والدليل ليس نموذجا محوسبا
It is in the real-world performance of the street.
بل إنه أداء واقعي على الارض
You can have fun with paint.
بإمكانك أن تمرح بالدهان
All told, we've created over 50 pedestrian plazas
وقال اجميع , لقد قمنا بإنشاء أكثر من خمسين ساحة للمشاة
in all five boroughs across the city.
في جميع الاحياء الخمسة في المدينة
We've repurposed 26 acres of active car lanes
لقد قمنا بتغيير استخدام 26 فدّان من مسالك السيارات
and turned them into new pedestrian space.
وقمنا بتحويلها الى مساحة جديدة للمشاة
I think one of the successes is in its emulation.
انا اعتقد ان احد النجاحات المضاهي
You're seeing this kind of approach,
لرؤية مثل هذه الافكار
since we've painted Times Square,
مذ قمنا بطلاء "تايمز سكوير"
you've seen this approach in Boston, in Chicago,
لقد رأيتم هذه الفكرة في "بوسطن" في "شيكاغو"
in San Francisco, in Mexico City,
في "سان فرانسيسكو" في "ميكسيكو سيتي"
Buenos Aires, you name it.
"بويناس أيريس" انت أسموها
This is actually in Los Angeles,
في الحقيقة هذا في "لوس أنجلوس"
and they actually copied even the green dots
وفي الحقيقة لقد قامو بتقليد النقاط الخضراء حتى ,
that we had on the streets.
تلك التي نجدها على الشارع
But I can't underscore enough
ولكن لا يمكنني التأكيد بما فيه الكفاية
how much more quickly this enables you to move
كم يمكن أن يساعد ذلك في الاسراع
over traditional construction methods.
في تخطي الطرق التقليدية في البناء
We also brought this quick-acting approach
لقد جلبنا هذه الرؤية سريعة التنفيذ
to our cycling program,
لبرنامج الدراجات الخاص بنا
and in six years turned cycling
وخلال ستة سنوات تحوّلت قيادة الدراجات
into a real transportation option in New York.
الى خيار حقيقي للتنقل في نيويورك
I think it's fair to say --
انا اعتقد أنه من العدل أن نقول
(Applause) --
(تصفيق)
it used to be a fairly scary place to ride a bike,
لقد كان مكانا مخيفا كي تركب دراجتك فيه
and now New York has become
والان اصبحت نيويورك
one of the cycling capitals in the United States.
واحدة من عواصم الدرّاجات في الولايات المتحدّة الامريكية
And we moved quickly to create an interconnected
ومضينا قدما من اجل خلق
network of lanes.
ممرات مترابطة في نيويورك
You can see the map in 2007.
بإمكانكم رؤية الخارطة في عام 2007
This is how it looked in 2013
وهكذا تبدو في عام 2013
after we built out 350 miles of on-street bike lanes.
بعد أن قمنا ببناء 350 ميلا من الممرات المخصصة للدرّاجات في الشوارع
I love this because it looks so easy.
أحب ذلك لأنه يبدو سهلا
You just click it, and they're there.
تضغط عليه ثم يبدو كل شيء هنا
We also brought new designs to the street.
وقمنا ايضا بتحضير تصاميم جديدة للشارع
We created the first parking-protected bike lane
لقد قمنا بتصميم أول منطقة اصطفاف محمية للدراجات
in the United States.
في الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We protected bikers by floating parking lanes,
لقد قمنا بحماية راكبي الدراجات بتصميم هذه المصفّات الامنة
and it's been great.
ولقد كان ذلك رائعا
Bike volumes have spiked.
مساحة الدرّاجات ارتفعت
Injuries to all users, pedestrians, cyclists, drivers,
والاصابات للمشاة وراكبي الدراجات والسائقين
are all down 50 percent.
قد انخفضت بنسبة 50 بالمثة
And we've built 30 miles of these protected bike lanes,
ولقد انشأنا 30 ميلا من هذه الممرات المحمية
and now you're seeing them pop up
والان أنتم ترونها تظهر
all over the country.
في كل مكان في البلاد
And you can see here that this strategy has worked.
وبإمكانكم أن تشاهدو أن هذه الاستراتيجية قد نجحت
The blue line is the number of cyclists,
الخط الأزرق هو عدد راكبي الدرّاجات
soaring.
بارتفاع
The green line is the number of bike lanes.
الخط الأخضر هو عدد ممرات الدراجات
And the yellow line is the number of injuries,
والخط الأصفر هو عدد الاصابات
which has remained essentially flat.
والذي بقي ثابتا
After this big expansion, you've seen
بعد هذا التوسع الضخم
no net increase in injuries,
لا يوجد اي زيادة في الاصابات
and so there is something to that axiom
وهناك شيء في هذه الحقيقة
that there is safety in numbers.
هو ان هناك امان في هذه الارقام
Not everybody liked the new bike lanes,
ان ممرات الدراجات لم تنل اعجاب الجميع
and there was a lawsuit and somewhat
وكان هناك مقاضاة واشياء من هذا القبيل
of a media frenzy a couple years ago.
من جنون وسائل الاعلام بضع سنوات خلت
One Brooklyn paper called this bike lane
مذ اطلقت صحيفة بروكلين على هذا الممر
that we have on Prospect Park West
الموجود في "بروسبيكت بارك ويست"
"the most contested piece of land
"الارض الاكثر اثارة للجدل"
outside of the Gaza Strip."
عدا عن قطاع غزّة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And this is what we had done.
وهذا ما فعلناه
So if you dig below the headlines, though,
لذا عندما تبحث خلف العناوين
you'll see that the people were far ahead of the press,
ستجد أن الناس كان يسبقون وسائل الاعلام
far ahead of the politicians.
ويسبقون السياسيين
In fact, I think most politicians would be happy
في الحقيقة انا اعتقد أن معظم السياسيين سيكونون سعيدين
to have those kind of poll numbers.
لوجود هذا النوع من ارقام الاستطلاع
Sixty-four percent of New Yorkers support these bike lanes.
64 بالمئة من سكان نيويورك يؤيدون هذه الممرات
This summer, we launched Citi Bike,
هذا الصيف أطلقنا "سيتي بايك"
the largest bike share program in the United States,
أكبر برنامج لمشاركة الدراجات في الولايات المتحدة
with 6,000 bikes
ب ستة الاف درّاجة
and 330 stations located next to one another.
و 330 محطة مرتبين الواحدة خلف الاخرى
Since we've launched the program,
مذ اطلقنا البرنامج
three million trips have been taken.
ثلاثة ملايين رحلة تم القيام بها
People have ridden seven million miles.
لقد ركب الناس لمساقة سبعة ملايين ميل
That's 280 times around the globe.
هذا يعادل 280 مرّة حول العالم
And so with this little blue key,
لذلك مع هذا المفتاح الازرق الصغير
you can unlock the keys to the city
بإمكانك أن تفتح مفاتيح المدينة
and this brand new transportation option.
وهذه الموضة الجديدة من التنقل
And daily usage just continues to soar.
والاستخدام اليومي لها لا زال بارتفاع
What has happened is the average daily ridership
ما حصل هو ان المعدل اليومي لركوب الدراجات
on the streets of New York is 36,000 people.
في شوارع نيويورك هو36,000 شخص
The high that we've had so far is 44,000 in August.
اعلى من 44,000 كانو في اغسطس الماضي
Yesterday, 40,000 people used Citi Bike in New York City.
البارحة 40,000 استخدمو "سيتي بايك" في مدينة نيويورك
The bikes are being used six times a day.
الدراجات تستخدم 6 مرات يوميا
And I think you also see it in the kinds of riders
واعتقد انكم ستشاهدون ذلك في الدراجين
that are on the streets.
الموجودين في الشوارع
In the past, it looked like the guy on the left,
في الماضي, لقد بدا الرجل على اليسار
ninja-clad bike messenger.
أشبه بنينجا يركب الدراجة لنقل الرسائل
And today, cyclists look
اما اليوم فالدرّاجون يبدون
like New York City looks.
تماما كما تبدو مدينة نيويورك
It's diverse -- young, old, black, white,
التنوع الشباب القدم الابيض والاسود
women, kids, all getting on a bike.
النساء, الاطفال الكل يركب على الدراجات
It's an affordable, safe, convenient way to get around.
انها وسيلة رخيصة وآمنة ومناسبة للأرض
Quite radical.
راديكالية جدا!
We've also brought this approach to our buses,
ولقد جلبنا هذه الرؤية الى الباصات ايضا
and New York City has the largest bus fleet in North America,
ونيويورك لديها اكبر اسطول من الباصات في شمال امريكا كلها
the slowest bus speeds.
الباص الابطأ يسرع
As everybody knows,
كما يعلم الجميع
you can walk across town faster
بإمكانك أن تعبر المدينة مشيا أسرع
than you can take the bus.
من أن تعبرها راكبا لباص
And so we focused on the most congested areas
لذلك ركزنا جهودنا على المناطق الاكثر ازدحاما
of New York City,
من نيويورك
built out six bus rapid transit lines,
انشأنا 6 خطوط لحافلات النقل السريع
57 miles of new speedy bus lanes.
57 ميلا من ممرات الباصات السريعة
You pay at a kiosk before you get on the bus.
انت تدفع في الكشك قبل أن تركب الباص
We've got dedicated lanes that keep cars out
لدينا ممرات صممت خصيصا لابقاء السيارات خارجا
because they get ticketed by a camera
لانها ستحصل على المخالفات عبر الكاميرا
if they use that lane,
اذا ما استخدمت هذه الممرات
and it's been a huge success.
ولقد كان هذا نجاحا عظيما
I think one of my very favorite moments
اعتقد أنها لحظاتي المفضلة
as transportation commissioner was the day
كمفوض للنقل هو اليوم
that we launched Citi Bike,
الذي تم اطلاق "سيتي بايك" فيه
and I was riding Citi Bike up First Avenue
لقد كنت أركب "سيتي بايك " للجادة الاولى
in my protected bike lane,
في ممر الدراجات المحمي الخاص بي
and I looked over and I saw pedestrians
ونظرت حولي وشاهدت المشاة
standing safely on the pedestrian islands,
يقفون بأمان على جزر المشاة
and the traffic was flowing,
ويتدفق السير
birds were singing --
والطيور تغنّي
(Laughter) --
(صوت ضحك)
the buses were speeding up their dedicated lanes.
والباصات كانت تسرع في الممرات الخاصة بها
It was just fantastic.
لقد كان رائعا
And this is how it looked six years ago.
هكذا كان يبدو قبل ستة سنوات
And so, I think that the lesson that we have
والدرس الذي تعلمناه
from New York is that it's possible
من نيويورك هو انه من الممكن
to change your streets quickly,
ان تغيّر الشوارع بسرعة كبيرة
it's not expensive, it can provide immediate benefits,
وهو غير مكلف وسيعود بالنفع المباشر
and it can be quite popular.
وسيحظى بشعبية واسعة
You just need to reimagine your streets.
فقط عليك ان تعيد تخيل شوارعك
They're hidden in plain sight.
هم فقط مخفيين في مستوى رؤيتك
Thank you.
شكرا لكم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)